Yeah, I'll talk about world models. Uh,
possibly the enabler for the next AI
revolution.
So,
there's a lot of machine learning people
I think in the room perhaps. Uh, I have
bad news for you. Machine learning
sucks.
uh you know basically if when we compare
the learning abilities of uh machines
with humans and animals uh clearly there
is a big gap um you know people and
animals can learn new tasks extremely
quickly and with very few trials very
few samples uh people have common sense
animals too physical common sense
there's a lot of tasks that we can
accomplish zero shot even if we've never
faced them before um and
how do we do this with machines? How and
you know we have very powerful AI
techniques that everybody is using but
they don't really handle the real world.
They don't handle continuous
highdimensional noisy data. Language is
easy by comparison. And so uh the real
world is messy. Language is simple. that
and and you know this connects with what
you know Vladin said earlier and uh
Gitandra as well. Uh the Marave paradox
that you know things that are simple are
difficult for computers and things that
are complicated for humans turn out to
not be that difficult for computers uh
like playing chess, computing integrals
symbolically and you know solving
equations, proving math theorems etc. Uh
so you know how is it that a 10-year-old
can uh basically do what you would like
a domestic robot to do and do most of
those tasks without actually being
trained to do them the first time you
ask them they can do it. They may not
want to do it but they can. Uh, how
come, you know, any teenager can learn
to drive a car in a few hours of
practice, yet the self-driving car
companies have literally millions of
hours of training data. And despite
that, they can't use those millions of
hours of training data to get a machine
to just imitating humans to uh to drive
at the at the same level of reliability.
Otherwise, we'll have level five
self-driving cars and we don't we don't
have them. At best in consumer car
business, we have level two or three and
uh the the robo taxi are engineered, you
know, very heavily engineered with
various uh sensors and other things. So,
you know, we keep bumping into this
moravic paradox and we really have to go
beyond this. If you believe that a
intelligence requires grounding of
course some philosophers and certainly
some language people don't believe
that's necessary but I think it is uh so
like Vladlin we're in Switzerland
outside John Pia he was a big influence
on me uh he had a debate with Nam Chsky
uh in France in the late 1970s where um
you know they were debating whether
language was innate or learned and uh
they you know, there was transcriptions
of that debate with, you know, people
participating in it. And one of them was
Jeanh was uh um
was uh
a a guy who had worked with Jean P who
was a professor at MIT and was talking
about the perceptron uh kind of saying
you know there's those simple machine
learning models that are cap you know
capable of learning surprisingly complex
tasks and uh you know that may be kind
of evidence for the fact that learning
is possible. Contrary to what Chomsky
was saying, um this guy was Seymour
Papert. He was professor at MIT and 10
years before that he had written a book
that basically killed the entire field
of neural net including the bas
basically pointing out the limitation of
the perceptron. But here he was 10 years
later arguing for the fact that those
things were actually interesting to
study. But anyway, so Jean P says
intelligence is not what you know, it's
what you do when you don't know. In
fact, he never actually said this. This
is apocryphal. Uh but there are other
psychologists who basically kind of
distilled his thinking into this
sentence which he never said. Um so he's
kind of quoted as as saying that. Uh so
intelligence is not an accumulation of
declarative knowledge. LM are an
accumulation of declarative knowledge.
not just but the main reason they're
useful is because they can accumulate a
lot of declarative knowledge. Uh
intelligence is not a collection of
skills. Uh
you can probably build a machine to
accomplish sort of any task if you spend
enough resources on it including things
like self-driving.
But that's not really what intelligence
is. Intelligence is the ability to
launch a drive in about 20 hours
or to you know learn any new task with
very little training or accomplish new
tot.
uh that's really what intelligence is
and that's really what Jeep means and
what that means is that we're not going
to have any simple measures uh of
intelligence because uh because again
any particular task you can always you
know if you spend enough effort and and
time you can always kind of crack it so
it's more you know how adaptive you are
um and you know this this connects to
something Vladen said like the notion of
AGI is complete nonsense Human
intelligence is specialized. The
characterization of human intelligence
is that it's very quickly adaptive and
we can learn new task. We all all of us
know different sets of uh knowledge and
have different skills.
Um and so it's because we've been
exposed to you know different
environments and we we've had to solve
different problems. Uh we're adaptive.
That's really what intelligence is.
Okay. So, how do uh how do humans learn
and animals for that matter? There's a
lot of uh learning that takes place in
the early months of life mostly by
observation. So, you know, two months
old baby, you know, can justiculate. So,
can develop a dynamical model of its own
limbs, but basically cannot affect the
world. It you know, it can't move an
object or anything. Uh but it does it
you know can learn a lot of things about
the world. One thing a baby can learn
really quickly is that the world is
threedimensional.
Why? Because
the fact that an object has a distance
every
uh point in the world has a distance
from us is the best way to explain how
our view of the world changes when we
move our head.
And of course babies don't move
necessarily their head but they are
being moved. So they they they see
paradox and sort of derive from this the
fact that the world is threedimensional.
We can do this with learning machines
today. They learn that the world is
threedimensional only by being exposed
passively to uh videos. Um so that's
that's an interesting uh uh thing.
And I'm going to silence my phone
because
it's actually
okay.
So um
so basic concepts like object permanence
is this is run really quickly. Uh
notions of stability, rigidity and
things like that. But then uh what we
would consider intuitive physics things
like uh inertia gravity
that actually takes nine months for uh
human infants
shorter for most animals.
And
if you put a 8-month-old on a high chair
and you put a bunch of toys,
uh, eight or nine months old,
the child would most likely
systematically take all the toys and
throw them on the floor and watch the
result. They're doing the experiment
that gravity actually applies to
everything.
Uh,
so that takes a long time. How does that
happen? What type of learning is taking
place there? They're doing the
experiment, but they can learn about
gravity just by observation as well. Uh
so if you if you show the the scenario
here at the bottom where a car is on a
platform, you push it off the platform,
it appears to float in the air. Uh a six
months old will barely pay attention,
hasn't learned about gravity yet. Uh a
10month-old will go very surprised like
the little girl. uh and that that's
actually how psychologists measure uh
whether a baby has learned a particular
concept about the world which is the
violation of expectation and we actually
we can actually use those techniques to
test whether machine learning system has
have acquired some you know some notion
of common sense uh so there there's a
lot that can be said about this uh Genra
and I collaborated on on a paper here
mostly written by Emanuel Du actually
and Genra had very little uh
contributions to it on on on this this
whole kind of set of questions.
Okay. But what is really what is
intelligence really if it's not an
accumulation of uh of skills nor an
accum accumulation of declarative
knowledge. It's the ability to
accomplish new task as I said solve new
problems with with without prior
training. Um and again agi has no makes
no sense as a as a as a phrase. uh human
intelligence is specialized and the the
question is is not do you know how to do
everything is it can you learn quickly
how to do anything
or a wide spectrum of of things. Uh this
is a a little kind of somewhat
philosophical paper here at the bottom
uh
written by some of my young colleagues.
So um here is a simple calculation.
There's still a lot of people
particularly on the west coast of the US
uh who believe that we're going to reach
what they call AGI okay uh by by scaling
up LLMs
uh maybe training them on synthetic data
maybe you know using a few tricks in
post training and reinforcement learning
and I think that's impossible uh I'm a
believer in sort of grounded uh
intelligence if you want but but you can
do this simple calcul population an LLM
you know typical LLM of today is trained
on something like
20 trillion words that corresponds to
about 30 trillion tokens and each token
is three bytes something like that
so the data volume is about 10^ 14 bytes
this would take about 400,000 years for
any human to read uh then compare this
with what a a four-year-old has seen
during his or her life that's about 16
hours of uh wake time
and uh which by the way is a small
amount of video. It's about 30 minutes
of YouTube uploads and uh we have two
million optic nerve fibers carrying
about one bite per second each. So the
data volume that a four-year-old has
seen through vision and probably through
touch as well is about 10^ the 14 bytes.
So for your old world through vision,
same amount of data as 400,000 years
through text
with all the human produced uh text
available on publicly on the internet.
Uh we're not going to get to anything
like humanlike intelligence by just
training on text. It's just not going to
happen.
Um,
so
of course you're going to say, well,
video is much more redundant than than
text. But in fact, that's a feature, not
a bug. If you want to train a system,
particularly using self-supervised
learning, you need redundancy in the in
the data. If you don't have redundancy,
you can learn anything.
So redundancy is a good thing. You don't
want too much of it though. Okay. So
then there is another question about
what are the right properties of
intelligent systems and in my opinion an
important property of an intelligent
system is the mode of inference. Does it
compute its output by propagating
through a fixed number of layers of some
neural net
or consider the alternative. The
alternative is computing the output of a
system by searching for an output that
is most compatible if you want with the
input. Okay. So you observe a situation
that runs through some perception module
that produce some sort of representation
of the current state of the world as you
observe it. Uh you can directly produce
an action. Okay, that's a reactive
system if you want. Or you could imagine
an action and then have an intelligent
system, the intelligence system figure
out is this a good action for this
observation. Is this something that you
know will accomplish the task I want? So
the objective here characterizes whether
the task the system wants to accomplish
has been accomplished or not. Think of
it as a cost function. It's not used for
learning. It's used for inference. Think
of it as you know negative likelihood in
a probabilistic inference model or as I
prefer to think of it an energy
function. So basically there the
inference
is a process by which you search for an
output that minimizes some energy
function at inference time. Okay that's
intrinsically more powerful
computationally
than just propagation through a fixed
number of layers.
And then contrast uh so the model on the
on the left uh is sort of LLM like right
take a window of of inputs run this
through a fixed number of layers of some
big neural net with a few hundred
billion parameters produce one token
okay then shift that token on the in the
input and then produce the second token
etc etc that's auto regressive
prediction and every token involves the
computation of you know a fixed amount
of computation running through a fixed
number of layers of some neural net. Uh
this is not a good model. It's not a
good model of reasoning. The way you
coers an LLM to do reasoning is that you
trick it into generating more tokens.
But that's not the way we reason. We
reason internally. We don't reason in
token space in language even. Um, okay.
Compare this with the model on the on
the right. Uh, which is a a slight
specialization of the the previous one.
Uh, you perceive uh the world or your
environment. You get some idea of the
state, the current state of the of the
world and then you imagine a sequence of
actions, a proposal for an action. You
feed it to an internal world model for
the system and the world model predicts
the outcome and then fix feeds this
outcome to an objective that measures to
what extent a task has been accomplished
or not. Okay. Then by optimization you
search for an action sequence that
optimizes this objective minimizes this
energy at inference time. I haven't
talked about learning yet. Okay.
In my opinion that's a much more
powerful model. Um but you need a world
model. Now if you do have so so I've
I've sort of uh settled on this kind of
uh
idea or architecture uh about five years
ago. I wrote a long paper about it u
that I put online in 2022
uh with some general architecture etc.
If you want to take pictures here are QR
codes you can get to it. Um
and uh
it's you know relatively easy to read
but kind of long
and
and it's really based on this idea that
uh reasoning and planning are essential
and they basically proceed by energy
minimization rather than forward
propagation and that for this to work
you need some world model. Okay. So same
process as I described before there is a
a few additional tricks. You observe the
environment perception module produce an
representation of the initial state of
the world but only a representation of
what you currently perceive. So you may
have to combine this with the content of
a memory to get a complete complete idea
of the state of the world or what you
know about it at least. Then you feed
this to your one model together with a
proposal for an action sequence and and
your one model predicts the outcome of
that action sequence. You feed this to
an objective an energy function that
measures to what extent a t a particular
task has been accomplished. So this uh
function output zero if the task is
accomplished and some you know positive
number uh if the task is not not
accomplished and perhaps measure some
distance to the task being accomplished.
So until you see you can have another
set of objectives that are guard rails
that would ensure that whatever
state sequences the the system is going
to take the world through is not going
to kill anyone or hurt anyone or you
know have any kind of uh delitterious
effect. And so a system constructed this
way can be made intrinsically safe
because it has to obey and you know
optimize the guardrail objective with
every output it produces. This is not
the case for an LLM. An LLM uh the only
way an LLM can be made uh you know safe
or non-toxic or whatever you want to
call it is by fine-tuning it. And there
is always a way to break the
conditioning if you want to jailbreak
the the system. Uh here this you can't
jailbreak a system like this. It it can
do nothing but optimize uh the guardrail
objectives and and the task objective.
Um of course if you have a world model
uh there certainly a lot of roboticist
and optimal control people in the room.
uh you can apply this role model
multiple time steps and you know each
action an action sequence can be
decomposed into a sequence uh the guide
rails can be applied to all the the
steps in the sequence okay that that's
the way you would use a world model and
the way you plan by optimization there
is akin to model predictive control MPC
very classical stuff in optimal control
going back to 1960s
ultimately what you want though is
something that can do hierarchical
planning all of us do hierarchical
planning animals do hierarchical
planning What is hierarchical planning?
Let's say that uh I'm sitting in my
office at NYU and I want to be in Paris
tomorrow.
There's no way I can plan my entire trip
to Paris in terms of kind of muscle
actions 10 millisecond by 10
millisecond. Uh which are the elementary
actions that humans can uh can do. Uh, I
can't do that because first of all, it's
too long, but second of all, I don't
have the information.
I don't know if when I'm going down on
the street, how long I'm going to have
to wait before a taxi stops, right? So,
there's no way I can plan the entire
thing. I have to do hierarchical
planning. So, what I have to do is at a
high level, I have to say, well, I don't
know how long it's going to take me to
go to the airport, but, you know, maybe
maybe roughly an hour, an hour and a
half. So, um, I need to get to the
airport and catch a plane. Okay, that's
a two-step high level plan. I don't need
to know many details uh to make that
plan. And now I have a sub goal which is
being at the airport. I'm in New York,
so going to the airport involves going
down on the street and catching hailing
a taxi and go to the airport. Uh now I
need to go down on the street. I'm in an
NYU building that involves uh walking to
the elevator, pushing the button,
getting down and walking out the door.
uh now have a sub goal getting to the
elevator right etc. So you can sort of
go down this entire hierarchy. And at
some point you get to a point where the
action you need to take. It's very
simple. It's something that you are
familiar with. You may not have to use
your full mental power to kind of plan
the action. You can probably stand up
from your chair without having to think
about it. That could be just a policy. U
but essentially u ultimately we want
systems to do hierarchical planning. How
do we solve that? This is an unsolved
problem. If you're a roboticist or an AI
for robotics kind of person or agentic
AI kind of person, if you're starting a
PhD on this topic, this is a great
topic. It's completely open. Nobody
knows how to do this or nobody has
proved that they know how to do this.
Um, okay. So now the big question is how
how are we going to train those uh those
models?
Um, okay. Hierarchical or not, let's say
non- hierarchical to start. So first of
all we have to figure out what
architecture to give them and a natural
instinct in these days there's an age is
to train a generative model and in fact
I've been working on sort of trying to
train world model like things for about
15 years mostly failing for the first 10
because I was trying to train gener
generative models okay what's a
generative model so uh self-supervised
learning has been incredibly
successful, astonishingly successful in
the context of language, right? You take
a a string of words, you remove some of
the words, um you corrupt the the input
and then you run the corrupted input
through some big neural net and you
train it to recover the missing parts.
Okay, that works amazingly well for
text. So there are original models like
BERT that that used to do this and LLM
is a special case of this where the only
word you remove is the last one. So that
the entire system is trying to just
produce the next word in a in a
sequence. Okay, but it works amazingly
well if you and and it it scales if you
do it right. It doesn't work if you
apply it to video. So if you take a a
video and then you show the initial
segment of the video to the system and
you ask it to predict what's going to
happen next at a pixel level, it doesn't
really work. like the representations
you get out of the system for your video
are not particularly good. Um,
and the reason is you simply cannot
predict everything that takes place in a
video. There's an infinite number of
plausible things in text. It's easy
because there is only a finite number of
words and so you can get the system to
produce a probability distribution over
all possible words or tokens in your
dictionary. But you can't do this with
video, right? It's just a incredibly
large number of possible video frames.
Let me take an example. Uh if I take a
video of this room, right? I start here
and I kind of slowly rotate the camera.
I stop here and ask the system continue
the video. You know, it's probably going
to predict, you know, we are in some
sort of classroom uh auditorium and you
know the room has a finite size. There
might be windows on this side and things
like that. There's absolutely no way the
system can predict what all of you look
like.
or which you know chairs are unoccupied.
Um it's just impossible. You just don't
have the information. So when you train
a system to make this kind of
prediction, you kill it. Now of course
you're going to tell me, oh but we can
train system to produce cute videos,
right? Video generation. Yes. But
this prediction usually is done in
representation space not in pixel space.
It's only a second stage that actually
turns the predictions into high
resolution uh high frame rate videos and
the system only needs to produce one
cute looking video. It doesn't need to
actually represent all plausible videos.
U so which is a much simpler problem.
Okay. And as I said I've been kind of
attempting to work on this for better
part of the last 15 years. So this is a
a 10 years 10 years old paper where we
try to train some uh neural net to
predict you know short video clips you
know two frames from from four frames of
context you get blurry predictions why
because the system predicts the average
of everything that can happen of course
you can correct that with latent
variable models like diffusion models u
but we which we didn't know at the time
we tried to use GANs and stuff like that
wasn't too successful
uh but you know perhaps using latent
variable models would uh would help
diffusion models in particular
um which of course produce cute videos.
Do they actually understand the world?
The evidence is no. Um so here's my
solution. My solution is a architecture
called uh joint embedding or more
precisely joint embedding predictive
architecture JPA which is shown uh on
the right. Okay. On the left you have
generative architecture. You observe X,
maybe you observe A, an action that is
taking place and you observe the result
Y and the system is trying to
reconstruct Y in its most minute
details. Uh with Japa you observe X and
Y and A but you encode both X and Y and
the prediction takes place in that
representation space.
Okay, major difference. What the system
can do is essentially eliminate from the
input
uh by constructing a representation of
Y. It can eliminate all the information
about about Y that is simply not
predictable,
right? And that makes the prediction
more abstract with fewer details but
more accurate in a way.
Um so
you know how do you train a generative
model? It's easy to train a generative
model because the cost is just a
reconstruction cost. It's just going to,
you know, you're just training it to
reconstruct. You can train it as an
autoenccoder, but then you need to
restrict the information content in the
code or as dnoising autoenccoder, which
is what a lot of techniques have
attempted to do like max autoenccoders
and things like that. So that means
taking an input corrupting it in some
ways and then training an autoenccoder
to recover the initial one. Uh and by
the way, uh diffusion models are a bit
of a special case of this of this sort
of general general thing of denoising.
Um so the bad news is when you train
systems of this type to learn
representations of images, you don't get
good representations. If you use the
representation of images obtained this
way, you feed it to a downstream uh task
that you train supervise. Okay, you
train ahead supervised. the results you
get are not great.
To get good results, you have to use
joint embedding architectures. All the
best systems that use self-supervised
learning to train an image or video
representation systems system
all use joint embedding. None of them
uses reconstruction.
Okay, all the best ones. And uh
either you let's say you apply this to
images. Uh either you have two views of
the same scene and you train a neural
net to produce representations and you
tell the system I want those two
representations to be identical.
Um or you you use this uh corruption
technique. You take a an input, you
corrupt it or transform it in some ways
and then uh you know train the this JPEA
architecture to predict the
representation of the original image
from the representation of the uh
corrupted uh version. Okay, there's a
big issue with this which is that the
system can collapse.
Now the generative models can actually
collapse to some extent like if you
train an autoenccoder without a
restricted
you know restriction on the information
content of the code your autoenccoder is
just going to learn the identity
function and that's a collapse. It's not
going to learn anything useful. Um
similarly a system like this can can
collapse and how can it collapse? it can
essentially completely ignore the inputs
produce constant representations and now
the prediction problem is trivial. So if
you just train a system of this type to
minimize the prediction error is going
to collapse. It's not going to do
anything useful for you. So the whole
trick of how you do self-s supervised
learning for joint embedding uh system
is how you prevent collapse.
And there is uh my favorite concept for
this I'll talk about other ways to do
this later but my favorite concept to
prevent collapse is uh is information
maximization. Okay. So you basically
come up with some objective function
that measures the some sort of
information content of the
representation that comes out of your
encoders and you try to maximize that
information content. Okay. So your cost
function is minus the information or
whatever.
Uh so there's a bunch of uh uh
techniques uh for this uh you know since
like the last six or seven years with
names like MNCR, NCR squared, WE cig,
VCRG and B twins. Uh the B twins, VCR
sigg come from uh people working with
me. Uh the other ones from other groups
MCR comes from uh uh Berkeley and MCR
squared from uh a colleague at NYU in
neuroscience. There was some chell uh so
but this idea of JPAG is gaining
popularity.
There's about 1,700 papers that mention
joint emitting productive architecture
spelled out uh on Google Scholar. Okay.
So how there's an issue with this type
of method which is how do you measure
information content? We need to have a
cost function that is a differentiable
measure of information content. So we
can back propagate gradient and maximize
it.
And the bad news is first of all we
don't actually have objective measures
of information content because all the
proper definitions are based on knowing
the distribution
of the the vectors or whatever that you
want to measure the information content
of and we don't know the distribution.
We only have samples coming out of an
encoder. So how do you how do you
compute information content from a
finite number of samples? Okay, that's
the first problem. Second problem is to
maximize something you would need a
lower bound on information content. So
that when you maximize you push the
actual information content up.
Problem is every empirical measure that
we we have are all upper bounds. So what
do we do? We come up with a good upper
bound and we cross our fingers
and we show some theoreans and whatever.
Okay. Uh so this technique uh and and
many others on on like the way to
properly explain how you you know how
you can train self-s supervised learning
systems and and every learning system
really is a framework I call energy
based models that I've been advocating
for 20 years or so. Uh it's basically
the basic idea is like this. If you want
to capture the dependency between two
variables X and Y and there is no real
functional relationship between X and Y.
So you cannot there's no single Y for a
given X right it's just a dependency but
it's not a function like it's a relation
of some kind of mapping but not a
function. Uh so indicated by the diagram
on the right here you have a bunch of
data points the black uh uh dots um and
so they indicate some sort of dependency
between X and Y. How do you capture this
dependency
given that you cannot run a function
that that computes away y from x? So one
way to do this is to uh
learn or build a contrast function
energy function that tells you
a point in this xy space is near the the
trading data or not. Okay. So think of
it as some some sort of landscape um
where the the black dots are in the
valley. Okay, in Switzerland there would
be a lake
uh and then you know you get like you
know level curves, right? As as you move
out you know outside of those regions
the altitude goes up. Okay, the energy
goes up right now. If I give you a value
for X you can infer you can give me a
bunch of values for Y that are
compatible with X. there are values of y
that minimize the energy right so it's
the kind of inference I was talking
about earlier inference by optimization
not by forward propagation
um but you can also possibly do it the
other way around if I give you a y you
can infer x from y and you can give me
multiple answers so in situations like
like video prediction where there is
basically an infinite number of possible
answers the proper way to train a system
of this type is to think of it in terms
of energy based models
uh and by the way probabilistic uh
models are a special case where where
your energy has particular form and the
way you train it as particular loss
function. Um so it's a slightly more
general framework if you want than
proistic uh inference and learning.
[clears throat]
Okay. So what to train an energy based
model you have to prevent collapse. The
collapse problem I was telling you about
before would be manifested by the energy
function being flat everywhere. You
train the system to minimize the energy
for a bunch of training samples and what
the system gives you an energy function
that is zero everywhere. That's what an
autoenccoder that learns the identity
function. That's what it it does to you.
A jetpad that ignores the input and
produces constant representation at zero
prediction error for everything. So it's
a collapse. To prevent collapse, you
need to do one of two things. One is
contrasting methods. You you generate
points outside the region of data and
you push the energy up. Okay, you come
up with some cost function that makes
sure the energy of the data points come
down and and the energy of other points
is is higher and there's a whole bunch
of them. And there is another set of
method which I have come to prefer
regulariz method which work by
minimizing the volume of space that can
take low energy. Okay, so if you push
down the energy of certain regions the
rest has to go up because there is only
a small amount of a small volume of
energy to go around of low energy.
Um so in practice
h how do you sort of reduce this to
practice? Okay, those one of those two
methods. Okay. So um let's go back to
this idea of information maximization.
Uh so I want to train this uh this ja
some measure of information. Uh let's
say I run a batch of samples through uh
through one of the encoders. I get a
matrix where each row is the
representation for one sample. Each
column is the value of one variable in
the representation for all samples.
Okay,
there's two ways to make that matrix
informative.
One way is to make sure all the rows are
different.
Another way is to make sure all the
columns are different.
You want to make sure the columns are
different because if all the columns are
the same that means every variable in
the representation carries the same
information and of course that's not
very informative. So you want to you
know each variable in the representation
to be maximally disentangled from the
other ones to give you an independent
information from the other variables.
Okay. Um so that would be an example of
what we can call dimension contrastive
methods which is a form of regularized
method and then at the bottom um the the
type of criterion that makes the the
rows all different those are contrastive
method or sample contrastive methods.
Okay sample contrasting methods are very
popular for certain applications. A lot
of the perceptual pipelines in LLM are
trained with a technique called clip
which basically is contrasting method
that does joint embedding between images
and text.
Uh but I prefer the other one. Um so
this idea that you need to find an
abstract representation of an input to
be able to make prediction is actually
very natural. We do this all the time as
humans. Uh we do this all the time as
scientists and engineers. Uh animals do
it too. Let me explain why. Uh in
principle I could explain or simulate
everything that takes place in this room
at the moment at the level of quantum
field theory or particle physics, right?
Could simulate the trajectory of every
particle in this room and that would go
down to actually simulating all of our
brain processes and everything. And so
in principle uh running the simulation I
could figure out if you know any of you
actually understands the word I'm saying
or not. Okay or if you are sleeping
right now um or if you're like totally
bored right uh okay but of course that's
completely impractical.
Uh and you know what we do in science is
we invent abstractions to allow us to
make predictions and those abstractions
ignore a lot of details about the state
the underlying state of the system. So
we invent those abstractions you know
from quantum field to particles atoms
molecules proteins organ cells organisms
individuals societies ecosystem
every level in this hierarchy is a
particular level of abstraction with
which we describe uh the world which
allows us to make
longer range predictions if you want
than the levels below
by ignoring a lot of details about the
level below Which is why
the the way to understand what goes on
in this room at the moment is more at
the level of psychology than at the
level of particle physics. Right? Now,
of course, physicists always make fun of
everyone saying like, you know, you just
applied physics, right? Even
psychologist applied physics to some
extent. Uh but in fact, you know, there
is uh you know, specific knowledge about
chemistry that does not derive directly
from physics, right? So, so this
abstraction actually kind of contains uh
new knowledge or information or
structure if you want that was not
apparent at the level below. So this
idea of jetpack really kind of
constructs on this concept that you need
to find an abstraction to be able to
make predictions. Uh let's say you you
want to do um uh you want to design an
airplane, you need to design the air
force for the airplane, you do
computational fluid dynamics, right? You
simulate the flow of air around around
the wing. U you you model the state of
the air in every little cube around
around the wing by basically the
velocity and the density and things like
that and and then you solve NTO's
partial differential equations and that
simulates the flow of air but in fact
it's ignoring a huge amount of details
in the underlying mechanism. The
underlying mechanism is molecules of air
bumping into each other and bumping on
the plane. But you never simulate
fluids at that level. It's just too
complicated and also it would diverge
from reality really quickly because it
has too many details. So you have to
ignore details to be able to make
accurate long-term predictions.
Um and so we do this in science all the
time. And so world models should not be
simulators, right? They should work in
abstract space. You should not be
digital twins, you know, that's a bus
phrase. They should definitely not be
generative models as I just explained.
Uh, and they should not be video
generation. So, a lot of people are
working on video generation and they
call this world models. It's they're not
world models. They are video generation
systems. Uh, so one one big message from
my talk is that if if you want to use
world models, do not work on video
generation. This is a different problem.
Okay. If you want to produce cute
videos, work on video generation. But if
you want to like control robots or
industrial processes or understand the
world, do not work on generation.
Um,
you want models to control complex
systems where you cannot model the
dynamics of the system by writing a
bunch of equations. Okay, if you have a
humanoid robot or you know any kind of
robot, you can just write down the
dynamical equations and then simulate
the dynamics of the robot and you can
get your humanoid robot to do some
assrults and and kung fu and whatever,
right? That's simple. Uh as soon as a
robot starts to interact with the real
world, that's a lot more complicated. Um
and and that is actually more difficult
to reduce to simple equations. But then
you know think about a complex system
like say a turbo jet or I don't know a
chemical plant or a patient uh or a
robot but a robot that interacts with
the real world in complex ways. You can
now reduce this to a small number of
equations. What you have to do is
basically learn a phenomen
phenomenological model of the whole
system the system you control and its
interaction with the environment uh so
that you can make predictions and you
can plan a sequence of actions to arrive
at a particular uh outcome.
So that's a world model. I mean the
concept is very old. It goes back to the
1960s. It's the root of optimal control.
Um and uh okay so now I come down to a
particular technique that I'm very fond
of which I think um we're going to
expand over the next few months and
years to do this information
maximization uh that I was telling you
about earlier and it's called sigg that
means sketch isotropic gaussian
regularization okay the trick here is
the following you you run a batch of
samples through your encoders and what
you get is a bunch of points in the
vector space of dimension whatever the
dimension of your representation space
is. We're going to try to make the
distribution of those points isotropic
Gaussian with the same u variance in all
dimensions. Why? Because
an isotropic gaussian is a distribution
where all the variables are independent.
Okay, so they're maximally informative
individually.
uh and it's also the distribution that
has maximum entropy for a given variance
but we don't really care about that. Um
what's interesting is that it makes the
variable independent of each other.
Okay, so how do we do this? Now of
course we don't have the distribution we
just have a bunch of points uh in that
space and it may be a high dimensional
space like 2,000 dimensions and we may
have you know a few hundred or a few
thousand points like how how can we make
sure this is uh this is a Gaussian. So
here's a trick. Uh the trick is you
project the individual points
along a single direction and what you
get is a marginal distribution. Okay.
Now of course you still have discrete
points. You don't have a distrib you
have continuous density. You have
discrete points. Okay. So one trick you
can do is compute the cumulative
distribution that those points give you.
Right? So it's a staircase
right? because you have discrete points
in one dimension.
And then what you can you can you can do
is you can ask what is the distance
between the staircase the cumulative
empirical cumulative distribution of my
points and the cumulative distribution
of let's say a Gaussian. You can do that
because you know what the Gaussian looks
like and for every point you can tell on
the staircase you can tell if it's to
the left or to the right of the ideal
Gaussian. And so that gives you a
gradient like do I move the point this
way or that way
in that projection.
Okay, it gives you a gradient now for
every training sample uh in your in your
batch. Okay, now if you make the
distribution, you know, by gradient
descent like optimizing this cost
function, it's going to make the
distribution Gaussian along the marginal
uh of that distribution along this
projection. But now there's a theorem
that says if you do this along lots and
lots and lots of directions in the limit
your joint distribution is actually
asotropic Gaussian.
Okay. So what we need to do now is do
many many projections for all of those
projections. Compute those gradients uh
you know move the points or back
propagate through the network change the
weight so that the points move so that
the overall distribution gets more
Gaussian. And
uh if you apply this to a distribution
like the one on the top left here like
an x these are actually two dimen two
dimensions among,24
and then you do gradient descent you
just move the points here. you don't
train a neuron net you uh so the
technique I'm advocating for is on the
left you get something that's sort of
gausianish
uh and this this really works in in
practice we've actually applied it to um
training world models that are action
condition and and we've used them for
for planning and it uh works decently
it's a very the the source code is
available it's very simple you can train
it on one GPU um And uh what we need to
do with this technique is scale it up
basically. There's a few other things
that we need to do but that's the the
main one. Uh and so in simple cases you
can train this world model and you can
use it to plan simple actions in like in
a push t or like simple robotic
situation in simulated environments. Um
so that needs to be scaled up but it's
it's sort of a good work. There is a
theoretical paper that uh we put out
just a few days ago where if you make
the hypothesis that the underlying
distribution of your data is actually an
isotropic Gaussian
and if you assume that the observation
you get from the world are some sort of
complicated nonlinear transformation of
those points like in this case like some
sort of spiral
uh transformation
you apply you train a neural with cigreg
on it, it will recover the original
Gaussian in the representation space.
Okay, so it's not a general proof that
it works in every case, but it's a proof
that if your original explanatory
variables are Gaussian, the system will
recover those variables up to a
rotation.
Okay. uh so we we can use those
techniques to uh you know in the context
of self-s supervised learning to train
an image recognition system uh and there
is another set of technique which uh I
should mention because they work really
well and they are the ones that have
been scaled up so far is conceptually my
favorite method but it's very recent and
we haven't scaled it up whereas uh those
other methods that are b based on
distillation we've scaled them up and we
got really good results both for images
and video uh with techniques like aa and
VJ Japa. So what's the basic idea of
those distillation methods? You you
still have those two encoders. So it's a
JA architecture. Um you take an input,
you transform it or corrupt it or mask
it or something and then you train the
system uh you know to predict in
representation space but you don't
propagate gradient through the encoder
on the right. Okay, those are two
encoders with identical architectures
and they kind of share the weights. But
the funny thing is that the encoder on
the right uh use a exponential moving
average over time of the weights of the
encoder on the left. The encoder on the
left gets gradient and gets updated all
the time. Uh the encoder on the right
gets updated slower essentially and
share the weights. Uh this is derived
from some intuitive ideas of some people
at at Google deepmind who are using
techniques like this to stabilize the
variance in reinforcement learning and
they realize you could apply this to
self-s supervised learning from images.
They call this bol
bootstrap your own latent. uh and there
is like a whole bunch of methods from
from meta in particular uh sinc etc that
use this exponential moving average idea
and a particular method called Japa
which uh I I show here it produced
really really good results and what
we're able to do with Jeppa is compare
the results of Jeppa with a generative
approach called MAE max autoenccoder
and it it it's not only better but it
it's much faster to train. Um, another
uh and another technique is is called
Dino. Many of you, I'm sure, have heard
of it. I I know some of you have used it
because there were projects in the robot
demos that actually use Dino. Uh, so
this is uh done by some of our former
colleagues at at Meta in Paris and uh
it's completely self-s supervised. It's
a joint embedding architecture. It's
using distillation but with various
tricks which I'm not going to explain.
uh there's a lot of engineering that
goes behind it and those systems
basically at at this time produce the
best generic representations of images.
If you have any type of vision task that
you want to to do that's probably the
best the best uh the best technique to I
mean the best encoder for images. Okay.
But what we've done is uh among the
things use dino as an encoder and then
train a world model and do planning. Let
me show you just a cute video on this if
uh if I can. Okay. So you have a initial
state here of a kind of simulated
environment that has pretty complex
dynamics and you have goals at the top
and at the bottom what you see is the
sequence of actions of a planner that
uses this trained world model to get the
world to a configuration as close as
possible to the original one in less
than 25 steps.
Um and this uh
has been applied to a number of
different uh uh scenarios uh like double
pendulum and and pushy and whatever. Um
now works uh really well. So we
recent more recently applied it to
video. So there you take a video, you
mask a big chunk of it and you train the
JPEA to again produce a good
representations so that you can predict
the representation a full video from the
representation a partially masked one.
Once the system is trained, you use the
encoder as a way to extract features
from the video and you train a head on
top of it to uh accomplish some task and
it it it works like really well at
state-of-the-art for a lot of
traditional vision tasks particularly
from video like action recognition,
action prediction and stuff like that.
But one interesting thing that I want to
mention instead of boring you with a
table of results is uh is that those
systems vapa in particular has has
learned some level of common sense. So
one thing we can do with VJPA because we
train it to predict what's going to
happen next in a video. We can train a
predictor to do that. Uh we can measure
its internal prediction error. We can
show it a video and monitor the internal
prediction error at every every time
step. Um this system takes a window of
16 frames. Um, so we we just slide those
those frames right on a on a video and
measure the prediction error with for
the next 15 16 frames.
And the cool thing is that if you show
it a video where something impossible
occurs, something unphysical, the
prediction error shoots to the roof. So
it's like the little girl in the one of
the early slides that you know looks at
the scene of the car not falling. Same
thing. Um, you have a video of a a ball
being thrown and the ball disappears.
Prediction error shoots through the
roof. Um, so that's interesting because
it's the first time, at least from my
point of view, that I've seen a
completely self-supervised system
acquire some level of common sense.
Tell you what's possible, what's not
possible. Um, let me skip this. It's
cute but nah it's it just says VJPA can
be used for planning and you know uh
this like new versions of this that do a
better job at planning and everything
but here is an interesting thing
remember I told you the way babies
learned that the world is
threedimensional is because it's the
best way to explain how you view of the
world changes when you move your head
okay so we took the representation
learned by some version of VJA called
VJA 2.1 and then we train a head on top
of it to predict depth from a single
image and it does a really good job. Um
it's it's
produced really good results in fact
better than Dinov3. Uh and
what that shows is that this system by
just being trained
to predict to miss you know fill in the
blanks in videos at a representation
level basically understands that the
world is threedimensional.
I mean understands with double quotes
understands the notion of object. If you
use the representation as input to a
segmentation system, it it works
decently well. Uh and for you know
various other things. Okay, let me
conclude. So
it's funny, huh?
So abandon generative models.
I mean if you work on LLM, of course,
but you should not work on LLM.
uh at least if you're in academia it
should absolutely not work in LM there's
nothing you can bring to the table uh so
abandon generative model in favor of
joint emitting architectures if you are
interested in you know uh intelligence
abandon proistic models in favor of
those energy based models I didn't have
time to really kind of explain why uh I
you know I made an argument in favor of
of those regularized methods or
information maximiz maximization
through through variables instead of
samples. So I contract methods which
again have a lot of practical
applications. I've I've been saying for
ever to abandon reinforcement learning.
I don't really mean abandon. I I mean
minimize its use because it's so so
horribly inefficient in terms of sample
efficiency. And I know there are people
here who work on this but uh but like
you know RL is like what you do when
you're desperate and there is nothing
else you can do. Okay, you like you have
to do most of the learning you know in
by observation
uh you know learning role models blah
blah blah and once you have good
representations you know you can use RL
on top of it because you already have
the good representations
uh you you won't require too many
samples sometimes you can't you can
avoid it uh and certainly if you're
interested in making real progress in AI
in sort of grounded you know AI for the
real world if you want physical AI don't
work on LLM don't work on generative
models either. So as you can probably
guess this does not make me very popular
in Silicon Valley.
Um and so I left Meta as many of you
probably know at the end of last year
and formed a new company called Emmy
Labs and the purpose of uh amabs is sort
of AI for the real world like you know
physical AI uh robotics is a use case
but it's not just that it's control of
industrial processes like anything that
is highdimensional continuous and noisy
for which LLMs are completely helpless
um this is the kind of problems we're
working on.
And that's it. Thank you very much.
[applause]
Okay. So,
I know there's many questions. Maybe
we'll take, you know, one or two, but
then we have to to wrap up. So, and
please quick questions and quick
answers.
>> Thanks for the talk. Uh I wanted to ask
about the guard rails that you mentioned
on the one of the earlier slides where
you also talked about MPC. Engineers
love MPC because they can put in their
constraints describe them in state space
like 3D space. But from what I
understand in your uh system everything
works in representation space. How do I
even get a constraint like don't bump
into the wall into this representation
space? Do you envision the system
learning the constraints by itself or
can engineers really put them in?
>> No, you would have to learn uh a very
small head on top of your representation
that maps uh that to your you know the
constraint that you're interested in. So
that part has to be trained but you can
train it with very small number of
samples because it's a tiny basically
just a projection
>> but you need a different encoder for
each kind of uh constraint that you
might want to put in. Oh well, you need
a different projector for for each
conraint, right? So if if your task is
to like open a door, I'm not talking
about constraint. I'm talking about like
a task objective. Uh you need some cost
function to tell you like is the door
open or not. Right? And so that might
have to be trained when you train to
accomplish the task. But basically that
requires two samples.
>> All right. Thanks.
>> Okay. I think we'll have to leave it
here. Thank you, Yan, very much.
>> All right. Thank you. [applause]